<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>DP100.1.: Ship</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded in XML from original publication</resp>
                    <name>Tom Elliott</name>
                    <name>David M. Ratzan</name>
                    <name>Patrick J. Burns</name>
                    <name>Georgios Tsolakis</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <ab>First published by the Institute for the Study of the Ancient World and the New York University Press, 2016. XML edition published by the Institute for the Study of the Ancient World and the Ancient Graffiti Project, 2018.</ab>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>R.S. Bagnall</author>, 
                    <author>R. Casagrande-Kim</author>, 
                    <author>A. Ersoy</author>, 
                    <author>C. Tanriver</author> and 
                    <author>B. Yolaçan</author>, 
                    <title
                        level="m"
                        >Graffiti from the Basilica in the Agora of Smyrna</title> 
                    (<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                    <date>2016</date>), 
                    <biblScope unit="item"
                        >DP100.1.</biblScope>.</bibl>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>Turkey</country>
                        <settlement>Izmir</settlement>
                        <geogName>Basilica of the Agora of Smyrna</geogName>
                        <repository>SMY</repository>
                        <idno>smyrna-agora-basilica-dp100-1</idno>
                        <msName>Smyrna Agora Basilica DP100.1.</msName>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>On the east face of Pier A100.</support>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout><rs type="execution">Graffito/incised</rs> Dimensions:
                                            <dimensions>
                                        <height unit="centimeter">25</height>
                                        <width unit="centimeter">22.5</width>
                                    </dimensions>
                                </layout>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                         <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote xml:lang="la"/>
                            <decoNote xml:lang="en">Ship</decoNote>
                        </decoDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origPlace>Smyrna</origPlace>
                            <placeName ref="URI" type="property_number"
                                >https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/550771</placeName>
                            <origDate notBefore-custom="0180" notAfter-custom="0300"
                                datingMethod="#julian">180-300</origDate>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>

        </fileDesc>

    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="grc">
                <ab/>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus"> 
                <p /> 
            </div> 
            <div type="translation">
                <ab/>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
                <ab>Graffito of a ship sailing on port tack, possibly a liburna, located on the eastern face of Pier A100. The graffito is partially damaged by a large gap in the plaster that has destroyed the ship’s stern and the left half of the sail. The ship is characterized by a large central mast, which is covered in a motif of crisscrossing lines identifying the rigging. A set of vertical lines, also meant to represent the rigging as well as the sail’s brailing ropes, departs from the yard and reaches the ship’s deck, defining a large trapezoidal sail. Above the yard, a series of diagonal lines departing from the central mast (considerably narrower than the portion visible below the yard and terminating in a very stylized καρχήσιον) are part of the κηροῦχοι. The keel is flat, and the prow is slightly rounded. Above the gunwale is a lattice motif representing the boat’s sidescreen, suggesting that the liburna was of the cataphract type. The prow terminates with a short triangular στόλος with no ἀκροστόλιον above it. From the keel projects an exaggerated ἔμβολος, in the shape of a stylized penis, with a diagonal line on the tip identifying the epithelium, confirming that the vessel has to be interpreted as a navis rostrata.
                </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <p>Bagnall, R. S. et al., Graffiti from the Basilica in the Agora of Smyrna (2016): 430-431.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
